Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Jade, you look gorgeous in this dress.
The eunuchs were stunned at the Imperial Kitchen.
This dress is the same as Lingrong's.
It is the tributary Glinting Satin from Suzhou Province.
My Lady cares about you the most.
She shares all the good things with you.
Do you think I look more beautiful in this dress than Lingrong?
The dress is equally beautiful.
But your earrings make you stand out
They are the new gift from My Lady, aren't they?
Lingrong comes from a poor family.
Even the best satin is a waste on her.
I will do the picking.
My Lady, look!
What's so surprising?
My Lady, is Jade wearing the dress
made of Glinting Satin that you gave to Lady Sourire?
She is.
Lady Sourire is very generous.
You would not even use such fine satin for yourself
and saved two pieces for her.
But she ... She gave it away to her maids?
Don't speak like that.
Jade is Sourire's dowry maid.
She usually wears better clothes than the other maids.
Even if Lady Sourire prefers not to wear it,
Jade is a servant after all.
What does it say about you
if Lady Sourire gives the dress to her maid?
Smells delicious.
The errand took longer today.
It didn't take long to get the water chestnut cakes.
But I also took some cassava starch from the Imperial Kitchen.
I was thinking of making tapioca pearls as your dessert tonight.
Thanks for thinking of me.
With Attendant An, His Majesty became more relaxed at work.
His Majesty used to work over 12 hours without a break.
[Emperor Yongzheng was one of the most diligent emperors]
I'm glad His Majesty can be relaxed by her singing.
You are very understanding, unlike the pettish Consort Fleur.
Come here.
Don't be scared, it's just a cat.
I heard that His Majesty received a cat from Persia ...
and rewarded it to the Third Prince.
This is the cat.
The Third Prince is a filial son.
He knows Consort Astuce is very fond of cats.
But when Consort Astuce brought the cat to me,
he sparked adoration by first sight.
So she gave him to me.
I named him "Pine Nut".
Pine Nut is very pretty.
Would you like to hold him?
I forgot that you are afraid of cats.
It is very considerate of Your Majesty to
have remembered such a small thing.
Come, sit down.
Although I'm very fond of Pine Nut,
I always have to keep an eye on him.
After all, any animal might bite no matter how tame it is.
Your Majesty must not worry about it.
Pine Nut is trained by Your Majesty and is very docile.
Is that so?
But an animal is even more unpredictable than a person.
We might be careless when we are too close with them.
Today is the Qixi Festival
[Chinese Valentine's Day, lunar July 7th]
His Majesty invited the concubines and the lords
to admire the moon at the Garden of Vibrant Spring.
Don't be late.
Yes.
On the night of Qixi,
I wish Your Majesties everlasting love and happiness.
Aiyo ... How caring Attendant An is!
It's a shame that we elder concubines forgot to propose a toast.
I see you are having some tributary grapes.
You should bring them to me.
Yes.
But Your Majesty ... you have the same grapes as well.
Why do you want mine?
They will be wasted if you keep talking instead of eating them.
I'd better eat them for you.
Your Majesty always jokes with me.
That's incorrect, Consort Astuce.
His Majesty only banters with Attendant An lately.
Don't make this about you.
People would say that you are stealing Attendant An's glory.
I am always appreciative when Your Highness has
any advice for my shallow talent and dull mind.
May I make a toast to Your Highness?
Consort Fleur has a big heart
[to accept the toast from a lower concubine]"
I'm a little drunk. I need some fresh air.
I'm not familiar with the garden.
May I trouble you to accompany My Lady, Madam?
Your Majesty, here's to you.
The garden is so quiet and secluded.
The Garden of Vibrant Spring was
the prior emperor Kangxi's favorite palace.
It has been rarely visited since he passed away.
Look, that is Tung Blossoms Terrace.
My Lady, if you would like to avoid the bustling banquet,
we might as well visit the terrace.
Tung Blossoms Terrace?
What a graceful name!
I heard that the Tung trees represent
the purest and most faithful love.
The prior emperor built the terrace for Consort Serein.
(sign)
Unfortunately, although Consort Serein
was loved exclusively for so many years,
she is now living in a Taoist temple.
What a shame!
What a deserted place!
After His Majesty's coronation, the Empress Dowager
was critical of the terrace's extravagance.
The terrace was gradually abandoned since it was rarely visited.
Even the most beautiful love could only
last as long as the floating clouds.
The love between the prior emperor and Consort Serein
lasted as briefly as the Tung Blossoms Terrace.
I agree.
Please wait here.
I will go up to the terrace.
You must be careful!
(Reading the plaque) Tung Blossoms Terrace
Do you not know what flower that is?
Who is it?
Lady Sourire always asks "who is it" when she sees me.
I believe my face is not very memorable.
Your Lordship always appears from behind.
I couldn't help being startled.
Nay, it was Lady Sourire who
walked towards me and didn't see me.
I had no reason to be hiding behind you.
I might have failed to notice
due to the lush plantings on the terrace.
But why didn't Your Lordship make a sound?
I saw you were not as happy as the other day.
So I dared not disturb you.
It wasn't my intention to startle you.
I was slightly drunk.
I thank Your Lordship for your concern.
Why did you leave the banquet?
On the night of Qixi, the moon is more worthy of my time.
Mm, exactly.
"When the jade-green dew meets the golden wind,
their love surpasses innumerable beneath."
It would be such a waste to
give the night away to the clinking of goblets.
Like Your Lordship said,
I am fortunate to enjoy bardic pursuits.
You seem to be fond of the flowers on the railings.
I am.
They are morning glories, commonly seen in the countryside.
But their rareness in the palace makes them delightfully unique.
The flower is also called "the face of eventide".
It shouldn't be in the palace indeed.
The palace does not grow ill-fated flowers.
Do flowers have an ill fate?
I thought only women are said to have a hapless fate.
They say it's such a lowly creature to grow in the corners.
It blooms at dusk and withers at dawn,
never to be seen by anyone.
Is that considered ill-fated?
I think the flower is out of the ordinary.
"The face of eventide" — they are
the beautiful faces under the setting sun.
Does Your Lordship agree?
We just wouldn't believe such a beautiful flower denotes misfortune.
Where is Lady Sourire?
Your Majesty, My Lady had a little too much to drink and
went to get changed in the side chamber [= powder her nose].
Sourie is a light drinker.
She can't compare with Your Majesty.
On a night for imperial opulence, it seems
inappropriate that we choose to seclude ourselves.
I'm a short-sighted person.
All I see is the "face of eventide" tonight.
I heard that you presented Attendant An to His Majesty.
Were you unhappy because of her?
We are sisters in the palace.
I hope I did not incur ridicule by Your Lordship.
In fact, it's good to have someone
to share His Majesty's favor with.
I would lament for you if all the other concubines
resented you for being exclusively beloved.
I thank Your Lordship.
Lady Sourire has a brilliant mind.
I shouldn't have needed to say anything.
But watching from the sidelines, I see
you might be walking into a morass.
That is why I chose to say the needless words.
Your Lordship's words are most appreciated.
As the emperor, my brother doesn't have a choice for everything.
I hope you will understand him.
I'm glad that I'm not one to wear the imperial mantle.
I'm not to be entangled in the
dilemmas and apprehensions.
Your Lordship's good name has been widely heard of.
You must be the man of many girls' dreams.
I dare not be greedy.
I only wish for one lady to spend my life with
instead of a cloud of concubines.
That is easier said than done.
Lady Sourie seems unable to believe me?
In my view, I must care for the person I love
so much so that she will not be unhappy in the least.
If so, the future Lady XVII is very fortunate.
Your Lordship's advice is truly beneficial to me.
You need not thank me, Lady Sourire.
I simply hope that you won't be overly favored,
following the footsteps of my mother
to a lonesome lamp in the temple.
Love is a rarity for the emperors and lords.
Their love, if any, can never be brought to light.
Just like "the face of eventide",
it's the flower that blooms merely for a night.
It's been a long time since I left the banquet.
I must go now.
It was not my intention to offend you the other day, My Lady.
Princess Wenyi's birthday is on the same date
when my mother entered the palace.
I was drowning my sorrows and forgot my manners.
I do not recall what Your Lordship is referring to.
Yes, I have forgotten as well.
Goodbye.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
What took you so long?
I went out for some fresh air to ease my drunkenness.
I saw a kind of flower called "the face of eventide" .
I was captivated and lost track of time.
The face of eventide?
I have never heard of it.
I found the crape myrtles in the garden are in full bloom.
I've had a few crape myrtle trees sent to your residence.
Mm, it is the season for crape myrtle flowers.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty is so thoughtful for Sourire.
His Majesty treats every concubine equally.
His Majesty is very thoughtful for you as well.
Certainly.
From Her Majesty to us concubines,
we are graced by His Majesty's impartial favor.
I will drink to propose a toast to Your Majesty.
I entreat Your Majesty to pardon my leaving.
What's so urgent?
I was informed that Wenyi vomited again.
How could that happen?
Her condition has been improving.
Has she seen the doctors?
Oh, yes, she has.
The doctors said she was affected during Cao's pregnancy.
And the sultry weather aggravated her condition.
She was getting much better.
I wonder why her symptoms recurred today.
Sourire, don't you feel it was odd?
What do you think?
Although vomiting is common for babies,
Wenyi's symptoms have persisted for such a long time.
If you think it's because of the summer heat,
Wenyi lives in Consort Fleur's Cooling Hall.
That is the coolest residence in the palace.
I don't remember hearing about
Princess Wenyi's symptoms before.
This is beyond expectance.
I hope she will get better when she's better taken care of.
Lady Cao is a loving mother.
Let's hope that Lady Cao and Consort Fleur
will take good care of Wenyi.
Are you suggesting that ...
she's using Wenyi to gain favor?
As a mother, what cruelty it is to do so!
I always want to believe humans are good by nature.
But I learned that life in the palace
can distort human nature.
That is why I have to assume the worst.
I heard that many concubines of the prior emperor
used their babies in swaddles to gain favor.
A mother should be the kindest person to her child.
But in the palace, a mother would choose to
gain favor using her child as a weapon.
Mothers could even do this to her own children,
let alone how hostile they were to other imperial heirs.
Sourire, let's not worry about them.
You have served His Majesty for a long time.
It's time for you to have your own child.
Me? When I don't have a child, I'd wish to have one.
But I would face unending rivalries when I have a child
I shall leave it to fate whether I will have one or not.
I often heard someone singing like a golden oriole recently.
It must be Attendant An.
Her voice reminds me of Empress Première ...
Your Highness.
It's windy at night. We should go inside.
Who would care about the health of a sterile woman in the palace?
Please don't be sad, Your Highness.
I don't feel sad anymore.
There's only hatred in my heart.
Your Highness.
I always remember how Consort Fleur
poured boiled safflower into my mouth.
After so many years, I can still taste it.
Your Highness.
We will find a chance.
We not only need a chance, but also the right person.
Your Highness, what do you mean?
When I saw her face for the very first time,
I knew that she would do me the favor in the future.
Easy, easy.
Look, what's this?
Your Majesty, here's the rattle-drum.
The princess doesn't seem to be getting better.
The imperial doctors are useless.
I apologize profusely to Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, it takes times for a young child to recover.
The princess loves to eat the
water chestnut porridge they serve these days.
We can ask them to make more so that everyone can have some.
Very well, I feel hungry too.
I will inform the kitchen.
The princess has a very good appetite.
She will recover soon.
I thank Your Majesty for the caring words.
Consort Fleur has been taking great care of her.
She worked very hard in the past couple of days.
My Lady, the princess vomited again.
She vomited the milk and the porridge we fed her.
How could this happen? She has not been
any better after two days of treatment.
Your Majesty ... I ... I have no idea.
Vomiting usually occurs when children are
under two months old because of their narrow pylorus.
But the princess is more than one year old.
Useless!
Your Majesty, please don't be angry.
We should let the doctor make a careful diagnosis.
After careful consideration, I believe her
digestive system was upset by a particular food.
May I check what the princess has been eating?
Your Majesty, there seems to be
something wrong with water chestnut porridge .
It would be prudent to call for the eunuch
who tasted the food before the princess ate.
Xiao-Xiazi.
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, the water chestnut porridge is harmless itself.
But it contains cassava starch.
Cassava starch? What is that?
Cassava is a tribute from the South Sea [Southeast Asia].
Its stem is used for making desserts.
But the roots and leaves are toxic and
must be processed with great caution.
Do you suggest that the food was poisoned?
The starch is harmless but it's not recommended for
infants because their stomach is weak.
It can cause infants to vomit, and die of weakness through continuous consumption.
Cassava starch looks similar to water chestnut flour,
so it's hard to distinguish when they are mixed together.
Your Majesty, the princess has been consuming
water chestnut porridge all these days.
This might be the cause of the problem.
How could the Imperial Kitchen fail to distinguish them!
It can't be the Imperial Kitchen.
They are experts in food.
I suppose ...
there was someone behind this.
What a vicious trick!
How dare they attempt to kill my daughter?
Huh?
Your Majesty, I pray that Heaven will have mercy on Wenyi.
As her mother, I will shoulder any punishment.
Stand up quickly.
Aiya, what's the use of praying to Heaven?
This must be an intentional act to afflict you and your daughter.
I beg of Your Majesty to pity Lady Cao and Wenyi, and
thoroughly investigate to restore discipline in the palace.
We must prevent the occurrence of such a heinous crime.
If so, let's start the investigation.
Tell the chief of the Imperial Kitchen to bring all
who have recently touched the cassava starch.
And list the palaces that have requested for it.
Not a single one to be missed.
Your Highness, here's the medicine for today.
Why did it take so long to pick it up today?
I heard the doctors saying that
Princess Wenyi had been vomiting.
So I inquired for more information.
Do you think it's odd?
I can’t say for certain.
(sigh) I'd like to go for a walk today.
I will drop by to see the princess.
Your Highness has been secluding yourself from them
all these years. Why would you trouble to get involved?
Secluding myself?
"The gusts of wind never spare a tree in seclusion."
I have checked the registry.
Only a servant of Lady Sourire picked up
some cassava starch four days ago.
It was for making tapioca pearls according to the records.
No other palace has requested for cassava starch.
Four days ago, I asked Jade to order
water chestnut cakes from the Imperial Kitchen.
She did pick up some cassava starch
to make desserts for me.
Lady Sourire, may I ask if you still have the cassava starch?
I suppose we didn't use all of it.
Did no one else request for it other than Lady Sourire's servant?
Yes, Your Majesty.
That cannot prove Lady Sourire did it.
Your Majesty, I saw Lady Sourire
leaving the banquet on the night of Qixi.
She seemed to be walking towards Consort Fleur's Cooling Hall.
Did you see it yourself?
I saw it with my own eyes.
I saw it too, Your Majesty.
And Lady Sourire was with Madam Jinxi.
Most of my servants went to the banquet with me that night.
The remaining maids were probably idle at the Cooling Hall.
Someone might have taken advantage of that
to tamper with Wenyi's food.
It would seem that ...
Lady Sourire, how heartless you are!
I might have inadvertently offended Lady Sourire
with improper words or behavior.
In the Governance Hall the other day ...
It wasn't my intention to cause misunderstanding
between you and His Majesty.
If you blame me for that, you can scold me or punish me!
I beg of you not to harm Wenyi.
She's such a young child!
It's not like that, Lady Cao.
I never thought you offended me in any way.
What you said at the Governance Hall ... did not cause
misunderstanding between me and His Majesty.
Why would you feel that I am holding a grudge?
Is there something wrong you did to me that I'm unaware of?
Lady Cao, it is indecorous to jump to conclusions
before a thorough investigation.
Yes.
There's no need for further investigation.
Your Majesty is partial to Lady Sourire.
Consort Fleur, observe decorum when you speak to me.
I have no intention to offend Your Majesty.
I'm simply indignant at Wenyi's suffering
on behalf of Lady Cao.
I plead with Your Majesty to make a fair judgement.
You must show due respect to the empress
despite how you feel.
She is the head of the harem after all.
Lady Sourire, say what you have to say.
I did not and will never do such a thing.
Did you go to the Cooling Hall that night?
I did walk past it but I didn't enter.
Jinxi was with me that night.
She could testify for me.
Jinxi is your maid.
How can we trust her testimony?
Except your palace and the Imperial Kitchen,
no one else has cassava starch.
And some maids witnessed that
you were heading to the Cooling Hall.
The princess started vomiting after you passed by.
I'm afraid you can't get away
by saying it was just a coincidence.
Although everything points to me,
I did not do anything like this!
Your Majesties will make a fair judgement.
If you say so, did you meet someone who can
testify for you after you left the banquet?
That will disprove the allegation against you.
I ... did not meet anyone.
I don't know if there's anyone who saw
that I didn't enter the Cooling Hall.
Take your time to recall.
Tell me if you can remember someone you saw.
If so, I will have to confine you temporarily for further investigation.
Believe me that I will find out who is behind this.
No innocent person will be unfairly penalized.
This is what you told me.
Yes, I believe in Your Majesty.
You will have to restrict yourself for the time being.
Your Majesty ... that night, Lady Sourire was with me.
Peace to Your Majesties.
I have always told you not to bow.
- Sit down quickly.
- Autumn.
I thank Your Majesties.
Why did you come out on such a hot day?
I heard that the princess is unwell,
so I came to see her.
I was hesitating to enter because
something serious seemed to be going on.
But I'm glad that I came.
Otherwise, "The Injustice to Dou E"
would be played in this hall.
You said that you were with Lady Sourire that night.
-Is that true?
-Mm.
That night, I noticed that Lady Sourire
seemed to be drunk.
I was worried about her and went out with Auspice.
I brought her into my palace ...
and we talked for a long time.
-Auspice.
-Yes.
That night, Her Highness and Lady Sourire had a
congenial conversation about the Buddhist sutras.
Lady Sourire said that it was getting late and hurried back.
Oh? In that case, Lady Sourire
has nothing to do with the incident.
Isn't Consort Honnête like a timely rain?
Consort Honnête would never go out during recuperation.
Why did you disobey the doctors' instruction that night?
I shouldn't have gone out given my persistent health condition.
But I heard really beautiful music from the Qixi banquet.
I couldn't help going out following the music.
It was such a delight to encounter Lady Sourire.
Yes, it was pleasure meeting Her Highness.
Oh? Lady Sourire, why didn't you mention
anything about seeing Consort Honnête?
I shouldn't have concealed anything from Your Majesties.
Her Highness did not wish anyone else
to know about her egress that night
in case it worries Your Majesties.
So I agreed Her Highness that I would not tell anyone.
I never expected this to involve me with the princess.
I believe that I will be vindicated
by Your Majesties' wise judgement.
And I kept quiet to honor my agreement with Her Highness.
Why? You don't believe her, Consort Fleur?
I'm not a suspicious person.
I feel that you are covering up for her.
I have only seen Lady Sourire twice.
The first time was on Wenyi's first birthday.
I should stay out of trouble when I'm unwell.
Why would I tell lies to shield an unacquainted Nobel Lady?
Rise.
Have a seat.
I'll call for the doctors to look after you.
I hope you didn't hurt your knees
wearing a thin summer dress.
Lady Sourire is a woman of her word.
It's reasonable that Consort Fleur has doubts.
I seem to have heard the maids saying that they saw
Lady Sourire walking towards the Cooling Hall.
We had better ask them to clarify
so that the misunderstanding will be resolved.
Tell us once again, did you see
Lady Sourire enter the Cooling Hall?
Your Majesty, I did see Lady Sourie
walking towards the Cooling Hall.
As for whether she entered it ... It seems that ...
It seems what? This is an unfounded allegation!
What about you?
Your Majesty .. I only saw Lady Sourire was with Madam Jinxi.
(sigh) What does Your Majesty think?
It's up to you!
Only, show no tolerance when anyone
"chases the wind to catch the shadow".
Yes.
As a warning to others, slap yourselves
eighty times in the yard.
Lady Sourire, may I take a moment of your time?
Lady Sourire, I wonder if you
would like a saunter in the garden.
With great pleasure, Your Highness.
I humbly thank Your Highness for helping me today.
I have my reasons to help you.
Why does Your Highness believe I'm innocent?
That night, I saw you walking from the
Garden of Vibrant Spring with your maid.
I knew you did not do it, based on the timing.
I was careless to not notice Your Highness.
I hope Your Highness will pardon me.
Don't mention it.
Princess Wenyi is adorable, but she has to
suffer so much at such a young age.
Although the princess is fragile, she is blessed
by the Buddha as a distinguished imperial child.
(sigh) Lady Cao was barely able to give birth to Wenyi.
She was pregnant at a bad time and experienced
difficult labor due to abnormal fetal position.
She narrowly escaped death.
But His Majesty adores Wenyi very much.
Although they are distinguished as imperial descendants,
they are severely afflicted compared to children outside the palace.
(huff) Lady Sourire, this was targeted at you.
You must be more careful in the future.
I was able to help you this one time,
but I can't protect you every time.
I thank Your Highness for your caring advice.
I will find a chance to visit Your Highness.
Don't worry.
It's inconvenient for me to greet you with my debilitated body.
Besides, it is beneficial for us to avoid seeing each other.
Yes.
Lady Sourire, Her Highness has to go now to have some rest.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Your Highness.
What should we do about this?
Your Highness, I have thought about it.
We will send a scapegoat to put an end to it.
Can we assure that everything will be fine?
Yes, I can assure Your Highness.
Very well then, as long as I'm not involved.
She cries all day and all night!
Take her away to pacify her.
Yes!
Bring her back later.
Yes, Your Highness.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.